hey I'll Scott here ever wanted to help
support the show and own silver at the
same time well a friend of mine
libertarian activist Arlo pinata has
invented the alternative currency with
the most promise of them all cue our
silver commodity discs the first-ever QR
code one out silver pieces just scan the
back of one with your phone and get the
instant spot price
they're perfect for saving or spending
at the market and anyone who donates
$100 or more to the Scott Horton show at
Scott Horton org slash donate gets one
that's Scott Horton org slash donate and
if you'd like to learn in order more
send them a message at commodity disks
comm or check them out on facebook at
slash commodity discs and thanks okay
guys Scott Horton show full archives at
Scott Horton org 4,000 something
interviews there Scott Horton org and
its fundraising time at the libertarian
Institute check it out libertarian
Institute org slash support for that and
on the line I've got John Kiriakou
former CIA officer the only one to go to
prison over the George Bush
administration's torture program not for
being a torturer for talking about it
and since then he has become an author
and oh did I say yeah he went to prison
for two years and now he's got two books
the reluctant spy which I wish I'd known
about I would have read it already by
now I think and there's a brand new one
doing time like a spy
that's coming out here any day now I
guess welcome back to the show how you
doing John hey thanks thanks happy to do
it thanks for having me happy to have
you here and then Oh May 15th so here in
just a week your book will be on the
shelves at amazon.com their virtual
shelves are doing time like a spy okay
good and yeah we could talk about that
so geez there's so many different things
I want to ask you about first of all I
don't think I know the answer to this
because I haven't read your book I know
that you were there I know that I think
we even talked about this before when
you were on the show once before about
how you were involved in the
rest of Abu Zubaydah in Pakistan and
your to some degree and I'm not sure the
timeline or what-have-you on it
your witness to his interrogation by the
FBI agent Ali su Phan and then also to
some degree by the CIA officers who
tortured him but I guess I don't know
whether you were involved in his torture
or or even his transport to Thailand I
don't know really much about that other
than what I just sort of outlined so
could you really fill us in about what
all exactly you know about the torture
of Abu Zubaydah in Thailand and how you
know sure
starting in January of 2002 I was the
chief of counterterrorism operations for
the CIA in Islamabad Pakistan and in
that capacity I led a large team in a
series of raids on the night of March
22nd 2002 in which we captured up as a
beta and I'm not allowed to say the
exact number but many dozens of other
al-qaeda fighters and - camp commanders
as well as others people even involved
in the Kashmiri separatist movement Abu
Zubaydah was shot and severely wounded
the night of his capture he was shot by
a Pakistani policeman and and we rushed
him to a hospital for emergency surgery
and from there we airlifted him to a
Pakistani military base nearby I sat
with him for the first 56 hours of his
captivity and spoke to him at length
after he came out of his coma after
about 24 hours after the 56 hours were
up the CIA landed a private jet at this
Pakistani military base three FBI agents
and I put up as a beta onto the plane
and he was taken to his onward location
which was a secret prison
you mentioned Thailand I'm not even
allowed to confirm or deny that it was
Thailand but certainly that's what's
been in the press
so I I was the chief of CIA
counterterrorism ops in Pakistan until
around the 1st of June 2002 I went back
to headquarters and I was in the
cafeteria one day and a senior
counterterrorism center CTC officer
approached me and asked me if I wanted
to be certified in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques I had never
heard that term before so I asked him
what he meant and he said very excitedly
he said we're gonna start getting rough
with these guys and I said what does
that mean so he delineated these these
ten torture techniques for me I said
that sounds like a torture program but
let me think about it for an hour why I
consulted with the senior officer like a
very very senior officer who said listen
this is a torture program you know how
these guys are somebody's gonna go
overboard they're gonna kill a prisoner
and someone's gonna go to prison you
want to go to prison I said no I don't
want to go to prison and as you said I
was the only one who went to prison as
it turned out but of the 14 people they
approached asking if we wanted to be
trained in these torture techniques I
was the only one who said no and and so
I was removed from the compartment so I
there was a period where I didn't have
access to any of the Abu Zubaydah
information but on the strength of that
capture I got promoted and I was named
executive assistant to the associate
deputy director for operations and then
I got access to the Abu Zubaydah
information again well what was
happening was there was an FBI agent at
the secret prison by the name of Ali
Soufan who was using a tried-and-true
FBI method of interrogation where he
builds a rapport with the prisoner and
in a relationship and little by little
Abu Zubaydah began to open up and I was
a beta gave Ali Soufan actionable
intelligence that disrupted attacks and
saved American lives it is well
documented in this in the Senate torture
report using primary source CIA
documents but the CIA hated the fact
that overseas the FBI had primacy in the
case where normally the CIA has primacy
over-seasoned the FBI has primacy
basically so George Tenet who was CIA
director at the time went to President
Bush and asked President Bush to remove
the FBI from the country and for
whatever reason that's never been
explained that's exactly what Bush did
and so that happened on August the 1st
2002 and within hours the CIA started
torturing Abu Zubaydah and immediately
he clammed up and never again provided
any actionable intelligence well you
know I read a thing there and I guess I
don't know if you count this this is
what you mean or no but I read a thing
that said that the first thing that they
did was they just threw him in one of
these little boxes and left him yeah
more or less in solitary for three
months they actually even get it
interviewing him at all they said well
the first thing we have to do is break
his entire humanity and so we lock him
in the dark for three months and no
one's asking him anything at them and no
one ever bothered to even discuss the
legality of this kind of thing I mean
back at headquarters certainly people
were talking about the legality or the
illegality and we know that that by
being you the two attorneys at the
Justice Department were we're doing
summersaults to to try to to make this
legal despite the fact that it had been
illegal since the end of the Second
World War you know in in 1946 we
executed Japanese soldiers who had
waterboarded American prisoners of war
that was an executable war crime in 1946
in 1968 The Washington Post ran it was
January 21st 1930 I'm sorry January 18
1968 The Washington Post ran a
front-page photograph of an American
soldier waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner and the day that that photo was
published Secretary of Defense McNamara
ordered an investigation the soldier was
arrested he was tried on charges of
torture he was convicted and sentenced
to 20 years well the law never changed
we changed so my question back then as
it is today is why was this torture
program illegal in 1946 and illegal in
1968 but then not illegal in 2002 if the
never changed well of course Ronald
Reagan's Justice Department prosecuted
the Texas sheriff for waterboarding in
1983 as well you're absolutely right
that's that's different than a national
security circumstance but I don't know
if that makes it different under the law
or not I don't think it does yeah there
but in our law though there is no
national security exception and you know
this is one of these issues where I
really believe that reasonable people
can agree to disagree but torture is
clearly illegal it's always been illegal
and if you want to make it legal then
you have to change the law plain and
simple you can't just pretend that the
law doesn't exist well and the thing is
about it too is that in US law it's the
US Constitution the first law bans
torture the Bill of Rights bans it twice
in the Fifth Amendment the
self-incrimination clause and the Eighth
Amendment cruel and unusual punishment
clause that's right right then and there
and then so this is my question too is
some will you ask it rhetorically but I
guess I'm asking it more lawyerly it's
the other Scott Wharton who actually
really knows the answer to this stuff it
seems to me like it doesn't matter what
any of those memos said it doesn't
matter what any executive orders said
that the log I mean never even mind the
US Constitution that you had federal
laws from the 1980s in the 1990's
enforcing the war crimes act and
enforcing the anti-turn and it seems
like well as you said there's no
national security exception the anti
torture convention explicitly says and
there shall never be and we don't want
to hear it and anyone that you try to
make is hereby null and void it's right
where you try it
etc like that so but then there's the
detainee Treatment Act of 2005 and then
now there's the Feinstein McCain
amendment of just last year am i right
that that's right read bans torture it
set that I guess I'm not really
altogether clear on how that is I mean I
know
in the 2005 detainee Treatment Act they
left the loophole they said and I guess
this is what I read about the the 2017
amendment to to the it's the
appropriations bill
an amendment to the appropriations bill
is that they say that you can't torture
you have to follow the Army Field Manual
but the army theater annual now allows
torture they rewrote it as a loophole so
John McCain has now passed two different
things one in oh five one in 2016 but
apparently they don't make any
difference because they're still allowed
to yes all this other stuff yep
technique in fact he he wrote it he
wrote her not that in today's New York
Times saying exactly that that that he
knows what an abomination this is and if
we're going to be serious about being
this global leader in human rights that
we like to tell other countries we are
then we really do have to be serious and
and the first thing we have to do is to
ban torture outright I mean III think
that it actually is already banned
that's certainly what what previous
congresses have have voted in and what
past presidents have signed into law and
as you pointed out not only are we
signatories to the international
conventions against torture well but we
were the primary drafters of that
international law and there are federal
toosey right that's right it's not just
that oh there's this international
treaty it's that then in accordance with
that treaty the Congress has then passed
laws that the presidents have signed
enforcing those treaties so precisely
yeah now we're up against where we
started here where you're the one who
went to prison for telling the truth
about it and that's because there
actually is no such thing as law at all
that all there is is power and these
people do whatever they want and in fact
the lady that destroyed all the tapes of
the torture is now the deputy director
of the CIA right right exactly there's
no accountability at the CIA there never
has been and I don't think that there
ever will be it's just the nature of the
of the organization but the reason why
it's allowed to be that way is because
there hasn't been leadership on the
oversight committees on Capitol Hill
since Frank Church was in the Senate
yeah well I mean in vice Feinstein is
relatively
on torture but that's it and she she
doesn't seem to take the rest of her job
very seriously
yeah I I feel the same way Scott she's
good on torture but otherwise she's been
nothing but a cheerleader for the CIA on
Capitol Hill
she's exercised no oversight at all yeah
well and in fact when they were acting
as though they were a co-equal branch
with the Senate over their spying on her
staffers and all of that she should have
staight them into the ground and
intercepted their role okay I guess you
guys are a co-equal branch with the
Senate by now who's kidding who here
it's 2017 this is CIA they're a lot more
powerful than the Senate that's just a
ceremonial thing for c-span and if you
were serving the CIA yeah both the CIA
and the Senate filed crimes reports
against each other yeah and in the end
they had the effect of basically
canceling each other out there was never
any serious Justice Department
investigation yeah and what we have is
is the CIA spying on elected officials
and their staffs nothing short of that
right well then of course the whole
thing is well who do you think you are
oh they're the CIA honey of course they
you know I forgot if this was from the
movie about James Jesus angleton the
Matt Damon movie The Good Shepherd where
they say how come you guys say CIA
instead of these CIA and he said cuz you
don't say be God in other words that's
the real government of America it's out
in Langley and all this stuff all this
white marble in Washington DC is just
for the rubes yeah
what's sad the true man all right well I
I over state the hell out of it and then
the former CIA officer says yeah no
you're right that's about that's about
the shape of it all right so let me ask
you this then I count five murdered by
the CIA in the torture program in the
George W Bush years three at Penny Lane
at Guantanamo Bay one in Abu Ghraib
prison and one in the salt pit north of
Kabul but there must be more than that
so tell me I I don't know to tell you
the truth uh I I know that there are at
least five Joe Hickman who's a former
Guantanamo guard and a friend of mine
and who has written
about this believes that there are more
and I've seen I've seen press articles
indicating that there may be dozens I
think it's one of those things we're
just never going to know
now Larry Wilkerson has said that a
hundred and eight different people died
in military custody right so we can
separate those out but you're saying
that you've heard that dozens perhaps
died in CIA custody yeah and again there
just hasn't been any accountability on
the hill why why are the oversight
committees not dant not demanding this
kind of information why aren't there
investigations to get to the bottom of
these questions alright so now Donald
Trump ears he says hey Harry no law can
stop me and the tougher the better
that's just the way he looks at all of
this stuff I say that old Mad Dog
Madison out of reinstituting a torture
program I guess they do have McCain
breathing down their neck about some of
this stuff so but that obviously just
raises the question of whether they're
just gonna ship them all off to field
marshal seesi in Egypt and have him
drive them all to death
see that's the wild card right there
that's the wild card I really do believe
that mattis and general Kelley at
Homeland Security are gonna be the
adults in the room on this issue Mike
Pompeo is not Mike Pompey is a follower
but I think the Trump was serious when
he said that mattis had talked him out
of it and then Kelley sort of reiterated
what Matt has had to say with that said
what's to stop the CIA from sending
prisoners to places like Egypt where
they are routinely tortured and and the
way that works too is the CIA will
always will always tell these third
country partners now remember you're not
allowed to torture them so you have to
promise us that you won't and then
there's a smile and they say yes yes we
promise we won't torture well of course
I mean that's that's why we send them
there we set them there to be tortured
right hey L Scott here if you've got a
band a business a cause or campaign and
you need stickers to help promote check
out the bumper sticker calm at the
bumper sticker calm they digitally print
with solvent ink so you get the photo
quality results of digital
with the strength and durability of
old-style screen printing I'm sure glad
I sold a bumper sticker com2 Rick back
when he's made a hell of a great company
out of it there are thousands of
satisfied customers who agree with me to
let the bumper sticker come help you get
the word out
that's the bumper sticker calm at the
bumper sticker calm well yeah I mean
she's there was that kid in Saudi Arabia
were the FBI agents even sat there and
watched and be tortured Abu Ali into his
fake confession his obviously laughable
confession that he was plotting to
murder george w bush and they sat there
feeding the Saudis the questions and
watching through the one-way glass
according to the reports they were in on
that one and that was the so-called pure
of snow FBI agents right right they were
the ones that are supposed to be so
clean that they can't even be in the
country when such a thing takes place
yeah and then that was the one too where
they let all his testimony be read out
before the jury but they didn't let the
defense explain that it was tortured out
of him by Saudi you know secret police
right or anything like this so the jury
went along with it that was when I
actually forgot about for a while for
some reason that just reminded me about
the oh yeah the turn and look away right
like my friend's dad letting me steal a
cigarette out of his pack when I was a
kid you know go ahead and torture him to
death and will pretend to not notice so
pretty much the same thing right
all right now so who else might they
rendition these guys to then if they're
not going to do if if we're presuming
for the sake of argument that they're
not reopening CIA black sites around the
world who else other than Egypt would we
look at for possible rendition trips you
know to tell you the truth that's one of
the CIA's holy of holies that's one of
the things that we can never ever talk
about in our lives
liaison relationships sources and
methods and anything having to do with
NSA so I think I'm gonna have to take a
pass on that one
well yeah I don't want you to go back to
prison but no but if I said to you
though but you know I read in the papers
in fact my wife nailed down one of these
stories about the former Nazi then so
yet then CIA base in Poland that's kind
of nice
and then there was Morocco and Romania
Thailand and boy
the stories of what they did to poor
Binyam Mohammed in Morocco can you
confirm those things or you say you're
not even allowed to say that what I read
in the papers is right on those
questions yeah in fact I've written
about this a couple of times and because
I'm a former CIA officer I have to send
everything I write into the CIA's
publications Review Board for a
clearance and they routinely redact all
of it all of it even if it's been
reported in the press even if it's been
confirmed by you know quote-unquote so
sources they redact it you know when I
write it all right I don't want you to
get you in that much trouble okay so let
me ask you this the story of Jeffrey
sterling this guy doesn't seem to get
too much attention not really sure why
but there are a couple of big aspects to
his case one of them is he's accused of
leaking the Merlyn katastrophe story
right well it didn't turn out to be much
of a catastrophe because the Iranians
never wanted to make nuclear bombs
anyway that's right what could have been
a catastrophe the the giant botched
Merlin plot to James rise into the New
York Times but then also there's all
these accusations of racism and racial
discrimination and I guess one thing
that I read said you know what they
didn't even care about the Merlin thing
it was that he was suing them and
calling them suing them on the basis of
discrimination that that was why they
went after Jeffrey sterling and
persecuted him and I wonder if you can
explicate that voice a little bit there
yeah and in fact they never even
bothered to defend themselves in in
Sterling's suit what they did is they
went before Judge Lee any brinkema who
ironically ended up being Jeffrey
Sterling's trial judge and sentencing
judge and they said your honor
we can't defend ourselves in this suit
national security issues we can't talk
about it
and she says dismissed with prejudice
just like that so Jeffrey sterling never
got his day in court
I I know Jeffrey sterling very well and
confident that he was a victim of racism
I confident that he was passed over for
promotion and eventually fired just
because the color of his skin and I
don't say that lightly I believe that to
be the case truly so Jeffrey sterling
ended up in prison convicted on seven
seven counts of espionage for allegedly
having conversations with Jim risin of
the New York Times there's been
literally zero proof that he ever talked
about operation Merlin with Jim risin
the only evidence against him was
metadata of 52 telephone calls between
Jeffrey and Rison over two and a half
year period but it was the same period
during which Jeffrey had his civil suit
pending against the agency and that was
a story that risin was covering but the
judge didn't want to hear that and the
prosecutors called Condoleezza Rice to
the stand to to have her talk about what
a catastrophe this was for national
security that that this operation Merlin
was blown to the Iranians there was
never any evidence that Jeffrey sterling
did that and indeed you know Jim Jim
risin is a two-time Pulitzer Prize
winner he's even said no New York Times
reporters gonna take one source and just
run with it
you have to have multiple sources and in
fact he has said that he spoke to
current and former foreign and domestic
intelligence officers well and that's
part of that story too is for people who
aren't familiar this was the thing where
they accidentally gave nuclear bomb
blueprints to the Iranians because
they're trying to entrap them with it
basically and catch them having it in
their files where but this was a huge
freaking thing so there's no mystery why
Jim Rison had multiple sources for this
it's not like this was some tiny little
deal this was I mean not that I doubt
anybody actually got in trouble for it
but it's the kind of thing where if it
wasn't the CIA somebody would have got
in trouble for that one that was a big
screw-up
so it was the idea that it was all
him even if he was I mean he might have
been account for confirming source or
maybe he was the original one but still
that would be far from the whole story
you're absolutely right
and so here's Jeffrey sterling just just
stuck sitting in prison now thank
goodness he's gonna he's gonna come home
at the end of this year but this is a
guy who's right and we're here at least
sick to you very sick he had a heart
attack about six months ago and has had
multiple heart episodes is what they're
calling them ever since and again right
now as we speak he's being denied his
his heart medication
so the only thing that saved he is being
denied his heart medication oh yeah this
is an ongoing issue he's filed multiple
suits he's filed complaints with the
regional national offices at the Bureau
of Prisons
repeatedly they've denied him is his
medication and then last weekend they
put him in solitary confinement for
three days because they said that he was
he was rude to a guard which is
ridiculous I wonder if they're trying to
kill him
you know he thinks they are he thinks
they are you're in prison so you have
experience I'm just gonna say gee I
wonder how that works but I could ask
you how that works I hate to say it but
doesn't really sound that different than
probably how most people with heart
conditions are treated right you might
get your medicine if we feel like it's a
the guards oh no what my bunkmate in
prison was the former mayor of Cleveland
right awesome guy I love the guy Frank
Russo terrific guy in on a corruption
charge they gave me 28 years he was 65
years old he had congestive heart
failure history of heart attacks and
they give him 28 years in prison
so we're sitting in our cell one day
just talking and he says that he's
having such terrible chest pains he
feels like somebody's sitting on his
chest I said Frank you're having a heart
attack let me walk you down to the CEOs
office and maybe we can get you down to
medical so we go to the CEO and he says
I think I'm having a heart attack the
CEO says tough luck buddy
he said sit call is Monday Tuesday
Thursday and Friday from 6:00 to 6:15
a.m.
you're gonna have to wait and go down
tomorrow so he went down the next day
they gave him Tylenol
which is what they always do they always
give you Tylenol and this went on for a
period of about four weeks well finally
he just collapsed of a massive heart
attack in while standing in insulin line
one morning and ended up spending eleven
days in a hospital he had open-heart
surgery while he was chained to a
hospital bed and then just today that
that was three years ago
just today I got a text from his one of
his daughters saying that he had another
heart attack he's now at a at a prison
hospital in Massachusetts he had another
heart attack and another surgery
yesterday they don't care if you live or
die there were four people who died
while I was in prison every one of them
from a treatable illness or a treatable
Mally you know the real scary part of
that is they don't care if you're a
mayor and nobody is good enough in the
club oh yeah even deserve the slightest
like you know you would like to think
that geez if you're a mayor at least you
get off easy but nope in fact that's
what I hate about mayors is that they
always get off easy but no it sounds
like not so much no it's it's what it is
is it's impersonal enough right either
either this guy's sentence was personal
or it was completely impersonal but
either way it's pretty bad it seems like
a pretty stiff sentence for an old man
and his brothers a federal judge and
even his brother can't exert any
influence to try to get medical
treatment for him Wow that there's just
there's no hope
literally when it when it comes to
medical treatment in prison there's just
no hope and now with Trump wanting to to
revive the the the policy of contracting
with private prisons it's just gonna
make it worse because the only way those
prisons can make money is by not
spending money on prisoners and the
number-one cost is health care yeah boy
I'll tell you what Shane Bauer really
embarrassed the hell out of himself
promoting war with
a couple weeks ago but his undercover
report on the incentive systems in the
private prisons being even worse than in
the government-run ones is really
something to behold
oh yeah and ya know I yeah the part that
that really sticks out of my mind about
that was I guess what seemed to me the
most innocent person in there that he
profiles that I remember was a man woman
whatever name China who was in there on
a prostitution charge in prison
I run a prostitution charge and then who
ended up dying of I believe he has
medical neglect and this is a death
sentence for someone in the prime of
their life over something that's not
even a crime in the first place
and yeah and just boy thought she might
as well have been a fly on the wall that
got swatted for all it mattered to
anybody you know that's our system and
it's all you got to do is to stop and
think for a minute what would our
government say if it was one of their
enemies that they wanted to destroy just
think about all the hype that Kenneth
Roth would put out about why we need a
regime change them for running this
system they drew we had I had a I had a
cellmate who was homeless man he was
living in a cardboard box under a bridge
in Pittsburgh and it started to get cold
so he purposely violated the terms of
his probation so that he could spend the
winter indoors and on the first day in
our cell he said guys I gotta be honest
with you he says I am severely mentally
ill but I'm on my medication right now
I'm afraid they're not gonna give me my
medication and if they don't I'm gonna
go nuts and I want to apologize in
advance and sure enough they took him
off his medication and a week later he
was certifiably insane and because he
was insane they put him in solitary
because they treat mental illness as a
disciplinary problem not as a medical
problem well he was only supposed to be
in prison until until April this was
October to April for violating the the
probation but because he went so nuts
and got so violent that they ended up
keeping him for a full year just by
adding time because every time he did
something they called it a new crime man
you know you end up you end up having
people in prison who are only supposed
to be there for short periods of time
and he'll end up spending the rest of
their lives or big chunks of their lives
incarcerated just because of infractions
over nothing yeah that was Nathaniel
Penn's recent piece about solitary -
where yeah you bumped my shoulder yeah
now you're into the hole with you for
ten years because some guard claims you
brushed into him you know yeah we there
was a doctor I on my in my unit he was a
Medicare fraud guy and he got 12 years
and he literally just brushed up against
a guard in the cafeteria capture is very
crowded you know you got 1400 guys
coming and going all at the same time
you just barely brushed up against him
and ended up costing him for weeks in
the hole and he apologized an accident
I'm sorry I didn't mean to touch you
yeah four weeks in solitary man well
alright so talk about your book then a
little bit here doing time like a spy
this is advice for the millions and
millions and millions of Americans yet
to be caught up in our criminal justice
system basically here yeah in a way you
know when I was sentenced my attorneys
asked the judge I had judge brinkema
just like Jeffrey sterling did to send
me to a minimum-security work camp and
the minimum security camps have no bars
on the windows there are no walls or
concertina wire you're free to come and
go as you please you're on your honor
not to abscond so she agreed and the
prosecution had no objection so I got to
the prison and and turned myself in and
they start walking me around to the back
of the prison I said no no I'm supposed
to be at the camp across the street and
the cop kind of chortled and said not
according to my paperwork you're not so
I told myself
take it easy there's nothing you can do
just wait until you get a phone so it
took me about five days to get access to
a telephone I called my lawyer and he
said he said man we can file a motion
but it's gonna be two years before we
get a hearing date and you're gonna be
home by then he said I'm sorry you're
gonna have to tough it out and so I
decided on that very first day that I
was going to use these twenty life
lessons that the CIA taught me in
training in order to keep myself safe
and to keep myself at the very top of
the social heap in prison um I asked
several a list Hollywood people to write
blurbs for this book and a couple of
them declined because they said I come
off as such an in this book that
they didn't want to be associated with
it but I wanted to I wanted to be
utterly truthful
you know prison is a nasty place it's
nasty and it's dangerous and it's ugly
and you're in there with murderers and
pedophiles a third of the prison was
pedophiles and organized crime and drug
kingpins and so I really tried to make
it as bare as raw as I could and so in
other words well I mean I guess give us
a few not don't list the whole 21 or
anything but give us an idea what you
mean yeah sure I mean well the first one
is is recruit spies to steal secrets or
anything else that you need and the
bottom line there is you just have to be
very adept at manipulating people to get
what you want and in prison I mean this
is gonna sound stupid because we're not
in prison we're in real life but you
might need a paper clip or a pen or a
highlighter or an envelope and all those
things are contraband and so you've got
to recruit somebody let's say somebody
who mops the supply room
or somebody who sweeps the warden's
office to steal it for you and maybe
he's gonna steal it because you're gonna
give him stamps that he can use to
gamble or because he likes the thrill of
it or because he hates the warden you
have to figure
his vulnerability figure out his
motivation and then use him to do your
dirty work there were others like when
calm is not to your benefit chaos is
your friend about stirring up the pot
seek and utilize available cover there
was one that we treated as a joke at the
CIA that actually was very serious in
prison
it was admit nothing deny everything
make counter-accusations mm-hmm I used
that all the time and so I tell I tell
stories associated with just about all
of these rules and and how I used them
to to get through two years in prison
well I mean since so many of us I mean
really all of us are living under the
threat of such a fate at any moment it
sounds like there's that book three
felonies a day about how you can't get
out of bed without fine labor yeah and
that's a very important book three
felonies a day by Harvey silverglade
who's a Harvard Law School professor say
he says that the average American on the
average day going about his or her
normal business commits three felonies
because we're so over criminalized in
this country hmm well and I think this
one is apocryphal I've heard it so many
times as you know first person or second
person there you know second hand told
we're FBI agents say in fact I'm
confused as to whether one of them
actually told me this like someone in my
cab at some point or something like that
back when that just look at just pick a
random person on the street if I want to
I can put them in prison for twenty
years and absolutely that's the way that
they can start they can just start with
their target whose life do they want to
destroy and then that's it you just grab
anyone at random just point at someone
and they can do it and they'll brag
about it and not even think it's wrong
absolutely true if they really want to
get you they're gonna get you and
there's almost nothing you can do to
protect yourself man it's funny because
when I started doing this shows like man
we better hurry up and stop the police
state for it gets so bad that I can't do
this kind of thing without really being
afraid to go into prison and now it
didn't work and here we are and I'm
of going to prison yeah not that I'm a
criminal but you know anyway I guess all
you send me your book it ever comes at
that point I'm gonna start knocking on
wood and hang up this call seriously
thank you very much for coming on the
show John appreciate it my pleasure
thanks for having me all right you guys
that is John Kiriakou and he's got a
couple of books here the first one is
the reluctant spy and the brand new one
coming out in a week is called doing
time like a spy how the CIA taught me to
survive and thrive in prison I'm Scott
Horton check out the archives four
thousand and something interviews at
Scott Horton org slash interviews
questions and answers stuff I got a new
one coming out for you here soon I guess
at Scott or nut org slash show and then
check out the libertarian Institute at
libertarian Institute org and it's our
big fundraiser right now so help support
at libertarian Institute org slash Scott
Horton show it's me and the great
Sheldon Richmond and Gerald LaBelle over
there used to be will anyway check us
out libertarian Institute org follow me
on Twitter at scott Horton show thanks
hey y'all sky here for rye guys t-shirts
reigai says w ry guys calm great
irreverent thought-provoking t-shirts
upholding a pro freedom perspective
inspired by such classic humorous is
Mark Twain HL Mencken and Oscar Wilde
they invoke the wit and wisdom of the
past to satirize modern myths these
high-quality shirts for men and women
look good and feel good and they make
great gifts use the coupon code scott
for 15% off my guys t-shirts a try guys
calm that's w ry guys calm hey i'll
scott you're on average how much you
think these interviews are worth to you
of course i've never charged for my
archives in a dozen years of doing this
and i'm not about to start
but at patreon.com slash scott wharton
show you can name your own price to help
support and make sure there's still new
interviews to give away so what do you
think Toob it's a buck and a half
they're usually about 80 interviews per
month I guess so take that into account
you can also cap the amount you'd be
willing to spend in case things get out
of hand around here that's
patreon.com/scishow
and thanks y'all
you